Shing sh
in
body
for
foree
uh everybody I'm sure you all know but
I'll just repeat a little bit that uh we
are in the M only section of the two
ways of explaining what is literal and
what is figurative and we're looking we
looked at a quotation from the Buddha's
own explanation of what he meant when he
taught the sutras and so we're in that
division now of the two different ways
of doing it we're in the mind only
division
uh just to repeat we started uh
yesterday afternoon from page 8 line six
where it
says
fore
uh there was a very uh great scholar in
Tibet named Jon who came before J or
contemporary I think maybe uh but uh he
spent uh many years studying the
question of what was literal and what
was figurative and then he composed a
book called n gatso which means the the
ocean of the real meaning or the literal
literal meaning and uh uh gisha says
that at this point in the text Page 8
line six that jetona is slightly
criticizing uh a Viewpoint of of jonang
jangan was very uh great scholar
especially in Tantra uh gisha says he
believes that Jon nangong was
responsible for translating some of the
kalachakra Sanskrit text into Tibetan so
no doubt he was a great scholar but on
this point uh concerning what was
literal what was figurative uh on this
particular Point Jetson Capa is
addressing a misperception by by Jon and
still there are people who who are
practicing
this
for
uh the position expressed by uh Jon
which they call the omnition Jon was
that uh when the three versions of the
pr parita there's a longer version a
medium version and a shorter version and
when they are talking uh about those
three during the second turning of the
wheel which we call the middle turning
of the whe then remember that we that
the Buddha was constantly saying things
didn't exist by by definition things
didn't exist from their own side and he
said remember that I've told you that
throughout this book now when they say
things have no nature of their own
they're going to be referring to the
statement in the middle turning of the
wheel where the Buddha said things don't
have any that things don't exist by
definition things don't exist through
any characteristics of their own and and
so when uh Janan was explaining that or
thinking about it he said you know it
seems to me that Lord Buddha is saying
that uh he adds the word ultimately so
he
says means ultimately nothing has any
nature of its own uh ultimately nothing
exists by definition so he says when the
Buddha adds that ultimately the Buddha
is restricting uh or he's he's the
Buddha is saying that it's only the what
we call the deceptive reality around us
the normal objects around us that he's
talking about when he says things don't
have any nature of their own and and
Jon's take on it is that the Buddha
wasn't saying that about emptiness
itself so according to Jona uh emptiness
itself wasn't what the Buddha was
talking about when the Buddha said
nothing had its own nature and nothing
exists by definition he said because the
Buddha said ultimately then the Buddha
was speaking about the normal objects
around us which we call deceptive
reality and he wasn't talking about
emptiness itself as being something that
didn't have any nature of its own that
was Jon's position and then jent cop is
addressing that misperception
here uh jenta is telling uh J not only
uh are you wrong uh you're you're wrong
with regard to both the mind only
position and you're wrong with regard to
the majika the middleway position so
either way take it even if we just say
we're going to stick to the mind only
position you're still wrong when you say
that and then much less during the
middleway position so you're wrong on
both
positions
uh then in the next lines where it
starts out
uh and then it says go down all of that
means when you uh Jona say that that
that description that things don't have
their own nature doesn't apply to
Ultimate Reality you're wrong and then
Jon CA says start saying you know you're
wrong according to this scripture this
scripture this scripture all mind only
scriptures so he's saying you're even
wrong just with regard to the mind only
School much less with regard to the
middle way school so he says you
contradict do gongo which is the
Buddha's own explanation of wdy men and
the sutras you contradict the writings
of Master asanga and you contradict the
writings of Master vasubandhu on these
points so you're already in hot water
when you say that even if we're just
restricting ourselves to the mind only
School
uh then Jet cab is going to attack him
in this way he's going to say let's just
stick to the mind only school okay and
you are contradicting the Buddha's
explanation of what he meant in the
sutras because you are ref you are
refusing that uh the words they don't
have any nature of their own applies to
all three attributes that are taught by
the mind only School remember we had
three attributes taught by the mind only
school so he says you know don't forget
the three attributes they are dependency
meaning things that depend on other
things uh which are the normal objects
around us and then there are nominal
stuff and then there remember there was
uh what do we call it total existence or
something that the third one remember
referred to emptiness itself so don't
forget that the Buddha in the second
turning of the wheel said that all three
characteristics are are empty or don't
have any nature of their own so the
Buddha said about the characteristic
called total existence which refers the
emptiness that it didn't have any nature
of its own so the Buddha's you're
contradicting the Buddha's own Sutra
where the Buddha says all three
characteristics don't have any nature of
their own and one of the characteristics
is total existence which refers to
emptiness so you're
wrong uh and Gish says if you want to
see uh a direct quotation from that
Sutra where the Buddha is explaining
what he meant in the sutras you can just
turn to page seven and there's one of
those quotations you know and it's down
there uh about 1 2 3 four five six lines
from the bottom and he says remember he
said oh and he referred to him with his
name and then he said uh there's no
things have no nature of having their
characteristics things have no nature of
having started and things have no nature
of being ultimate and that third one
means The Emptiness of things itself
doesn't have a nature the Third
attribute of what we call Total
existence doesn't have a nature of its
own so in that quotation alone Gish says
on the page before from that book by the
Buddha he states that that emptiness
itself doesn't have a nature of its own
so what are you talking about
Jan
okay uh we'll get more on that later I'm
just giving you a little uh brief
description of it but of course it's
going to come more later on the same
point uh on page 13 the uh the more
detailed explanation of this point
begins and he's not going to go there
now I don't think but he just wants you
to know that's where it
starts seven lines from the bottom on
page
and uh that's a direct quotation from uh
do gondel from the Buddhist explanation
of what he meant the sutras that says um
moreover uh the attribute that we call
Total existence doesn't have any nature
of its own either so that's another
quotation directly from Lord Buddha that
refutes the idea of
Jon uh the explanation before that we
just talked about before is what is the
shorter one and this is where we
consider this the longer one and the
more detailed one and there'll be a more
detailed explanation of this point
coming up on page
13 uh I'm just giving you a rough a
rough out of the of this point and later
on you're going to get hit with it big
time
okay
uh when uh and then when jetuka goes on
to say not only do you contradict this
Sutra where the Buddha explained what he
meant the sutus you're also
contradicting the two brothers right
which is Master s and master Bas Bandu
and then gisha says you know if you want
to see how he contradicts Master s you
can just go back to page seven look at
the last line where it
says uh
Master wrote This is called the summary
and I was just wondering which the
summary it was and master wrote a couple
of the summaries and he says he thinks
it's a certain one uh and then it
says
uh so here's Master a saying uh remember
what he said yesterday he said uh what
did the Buddha mean if you ask me you
know if you come and ask me what did the
Buddha mean when he said that uh no
existing phenomenon has any nature of
its own mea I'll tell you you know what
is it uh due to the due to the needs of
the disciples the Buddha taught three
lacks of self-existence or self- nature
and he he said that three different
things don't have any self nature as you
know he's referring to the three
characteristics or attributes of the M
only school as you know total existence
is in there and as you know to existence
refers to emptiness so the Buddha said
according to master s that emptiness
doesn't have its own nature so you
contradict Master s right
there
question uh you're also contradicting
Master basab Bandu uh you can get a
quotation on page 8 line three from his
30 versus uh where he says look uh what
did the Buddha have in mind when he said
there wasn't any nature he had in mind
that there wasn't any of those three
Natures meaning the self-existent nature
of the three attributes as you know one
of the attributes is is emptiness and so
you're also contradicting Master basab
Bandu so there's a proof that you're
contradicting the Buddha Master s and
master B
uh so we've demonstrated quite
thoroughly that you contradict the
entire teaching said the mind only
school and we finished that now let's go
on to the middle way School let's prove
that you contradicting that this is a
no-brainer uh in the middle turning of
the wheel the medium turning the middle
turning of the wheel the Buddha directly
said uh everything this is my this is
maik people speaking right he said
directly everything from physical matter
on up to everything uh doesn't have any
nature of its own whether you say it
doesn't exist by definition or whether
you say it doesn't exist ultimately by
definition it all boils down to the same
thing and when you say all existing
phenomena starting with physical matter
on up to everything else of course
emptiness itself is in there so you
contradict the majima schools also when
you say that the Buddha didn't mean to
say that emptiness itself didn't have an
ultimate
nature
fore
six line from the bottom and there
begins a discussion of uh how did the
Buddha teach that nothing had a nature
of its own in the second turning of the
wheel in the me middle turning of the
wheel and he he went through the he he
could have gone through all the
categories of everything that existed
you know he could have gone through
every single category of all the things
that exist in the universe and say this
doesn't exist by definition this doesn't
exist by definition this doesn't have a
nature of its own this doesn't have a
nature of its own and it could have gone
through all the different
classifications of all the things that
exist in the world there's no time to do
that okay I mean he couldn't sit there
and go through everything that existed
in the universe and say and say about
each thing describe about each thing how
it didn't have any nature of its own so
you know uh with skillful means uh the
Buddha chose uh to to classify
everything into three groups you know if
you could say this group group number
one group number two group number three
they don't have any nature of their own
then that would be a very skillful Way
by Lord Buddha to to summarize every
existing object and he wouldn't have to
go into the lack of self- nature of
every existing object so in a very
skillful way Lord Buddha has chosen or
described these three attributes right
which means things that depend on the
power of other things uh things that uh
what we call Total existence or empty
things and then all the other unchanging
things which refers to what we call
nominal stuff right so very skillfully
the Buddha has chosen these three
categories or these three attributes and
has demonstrated that each of these
three doesn't have their own nature and
that gets him out of having to spend his
whole uni you know eternity trying to
explain the emptiness of every single
object in the
universe
for
uh you know for example if we wanted to
go about proving that there wasn't any
human being in the world that didn't
have a mind okay so you know we could go
to America and pick out people one by
one and stand them in line say stand in
line you know and uh pick the first guy
out you stand here you know uh look this
guy is not a person that doesn't have a
mind he's a person that doesn't have a
mind okay now you go now second guy come
and you prove that that guy has a mind
you know you say look he's not a person
who doesn't have a mind and you say okay
then you you could go through the whole
population in the United States that way
it would be a little inconvenient and
then you'd have to do Tibet and then
you'd have to do India for example so
it'd be like these three nations of
people that you have to go one by one
through them and demonstrate that each
guy is such that they don't not have a
mind right uh but uh it'd be a lot
easier just to sit there and say nobody
among the whole American population
doesn't have a mind nobody among the
Indian population doesn't have a mind no
known the Tibetan population doesn't
have a mind and in this way with three
simple phrases the population of America
population of population of India you
can cover all the uh existing human
beings of those three countries and then
about you say about those three none of
them is such that they don't have a mind
to prove that they all do have a mind so
it's the same thing with proving that
things don't have any nature of their
own uh you can just say look uh th those
three categories of things okay things
that depend on others uh things that are
and then things that are uh what do you
call nominal stuff right you could just
divide it into these c three three
categories and say everything in those
three categories or nothing in those
three categories has any nature of its
own you've covered everything so it's a
very similar
example uh so you know we can just
summarize it in a very simple way uh
when don't forget that we are in the
mind only School we're talking about the
from the mind only Viewpoint during the
second turning of the wheel uh the
Buddha was speaking about the The
Emptiness of three different or the the
lack of self- nature of three different
categories and in there is there a
category of emptiness and and did the
Buddha teach do you guys think uh that
emptiness itself didn't have any nature
of its
own of course
he says let's hear an answer
here uh and as you guys can easily grasp
uh in the mind only I'm sorry in in the
middle way School uh they just say look
in the secretary of the wheel Buddha
said everything from physical matter up
to everything uh is such that it doesn't
have its own nature so automatically you
get uh emptiness covered in there and
obviously the Buddha taught that he said
all existing phenomena emptiness is
going to be included in there there's no
big deal about the mind only School
believing that uh the Buddha did teach
that emptiness itself doesn't have a
self
nature
for
uh so the Buddha you know we say that
the Buddha in the secondary of the wheel
went through a a bunch of different
categories he did describe a lot of
categories he went through like 108
different categories he spoke about 18
distinct different kinds of emptiness
and so he did go through all these
categories he did speak all of that
obviously if he talked about 108
different kinds of existing phenomena
and obviously if he treated 18 different
kinds of emptiness then I guess he was
talking about emptiness when he
described that that things didn't have a
self nature so I can't imagine who with
any kind of brain would say that uh that
emptiness itself was such that it didn't
have a nature of its own uh and gisha
says you know we just proved that
everybody had a brain but jetona is
seeing here that anybody with a brain
could understand that he seems to be imp
that jonan maybe didn't have a brain but
we have to agree that jonan did have a
brain so probably when he said anyone
with a brain could understand that he
was probably meaning that um he didn't
have the brains to think about this uh
when he was talking like
that
uh there's a new expression going around
the monaster nowadays called The Man
means like uh no no spinal cord or no uh
no brain matter no gray matter they call
them gray grayless meaning no gray
matter and uh but you know it's not
really literal you know people do have
some gray
matter
there's a lot of new Expressions coming
around the monastery especially you know
people come from Tibet new refugees come
to Tibet and they don't know any Hindi
yet so you know people are talking about
them they use Hindi nicknames for them
and one is katcha katcha means uh again
say that means a like a a fruit that's
not ripe yet meaning they're tender what
do you call Tender feet newcomers so
they call them oh hey ca ca ca and uh
and they they don't know what language
it is and they don't know what it means
but that's how you get you know new
words floating around the
monastery what it's kind of like that
brainless
grayless just
joking
uh now we're going to get to the sixth
line sorry uh seventh line from the
bottom of page nine which is uh a new
category uh it's category number two
which it says uh a more detailed
explanation and here although uh the
subject matter and the points are going
to be the same as before there's going
to be a little more detail on them now
for
uh you know in the actual quotation from
the Sutra where the Buddha explains his
own sutras the intent of his own sutras
uh he doesn't
really give the name of the three
attributes that the mind only School
follows uh very clearly he just says
there's no nature to the characteristics
of things there's no nature to the
beginning of things and there's no
nature to Ultimate to the ultimate
that's all he says he doesn't clearly
State uh what it is that doesn't have a
characteristic how it is they don't have
a characteristic what it is that doesn't
start what it is that how it doesn't
start he doesn't get into that so Jess
kaba's Point here in this next section
is what is how do we explain the actual
wording which is kind of obscure uh
where the Buddha says things don't have
any characteristics things don't have
any beginning or starting and things
don't have any ultimate there's no
ultimate you know what is he those three
things don't have any nature of their
own which is actually referring to the
three attributes of the Mind only school
but he doesn't say those he doesn't use
that exact wording so jessen is going to
go through and explain to you
particularly in the first case what is
it that doesn't have a characteristic
how is it that it doesn't have a
characteristic so he's going to go into
that detail
now
uh he says actually Lord Buddha himself
later on in his own Sutra explains what
he meant by those three Expressions so
the Sutra itself is brief in the uh in
the case that we already had and the
Sutra itself is going to help explain
what the Sutra meant is further down in
the Sutra itself so now we're going to
get sort of a longer explanation not
only by jsaa but in the Sutra
itself
uh so if you think about it we're going
to go now into two different discussions
one is going to be the Sutra itself
explaining in more detail what the Sutra
itself said and then you're going to
have Jetson Capa based on that
explanation by the Sutra giving you a
further clarification of what the Sutra
means when it explains in more detail
what the Sutra meant when it was when it
made those briefer
statements okay
uh I left something out uh on that last
explanation and I want to go back and
just insert something
here
uh there's a particular uh unique
characteristic of the way that Jetson
Kapa approached his writing and and his
teaching uh when he wanted to uh if you
and I were going to try to refute the
ideas of of a person that was living uh
in our time or or around these days we
would say so and so living in such and
such a country uh at such and such an
address uh whose name is like such and
such uh has got this stupid idea and
then we would say he's wrong on that
he's wrong on that he's wrong on that
he's really stupid I'm really great I
got this really good idea here's what I
think you know and it would be a very
personal conf frontation in a sense but
Jon says J style wasn't like that how
does he treat uh the omnicient it's
called he's called the
omnicient and andaba doesn't approach
things like that he says he doesn't say
oh the omnition J thinks that he says
well you know a couple of people have
expressed the idea that you know blah
blah blah and then he he he sort of then
he goes up then he undertakes to tear it
apart but he doesn't directly state in
this text that he's talking about the
omnicient J he's just saying well you
know some people say that and that's
very much Justa style he does not attack
the person he's attacking the idea uh
and and then saying well you know some
people are saying that you know like
that uh there are really uh two reasons
why Juna uh doesn't choose to name the
person whose idea he's
attacking
uh the first reason why JS Kaa doesn't
choose CH to name uh the person who has
these ideas directly is is an indication
that jetuka himself possesses the three
fine spiritual qualities that we call uh
wisdom uh Holiness and Purity ketum and
uh it's to indicate particularly that he
has the second quality which is called
Holiness meaning uh he he he doesn't
want to get into uh he he wants to avoid
uh the implication that he is this big
guy and the other guy is this little guy
and that and that he is this uh great
scholar and the other guy doesn't know
anything and that and that he's up here
and he's down there he doesn't out of
respect for his morality out of respect
for his own morality he doesn't want to
get into a situation where he's uh
putting himself up and putting the other
guy down he wants to avoid that so the
first reason why jetsun Kaba doesn't
name the other person is that he he
wants to stick to his vows and his vows
require him not to get into a situation
where he's like criticizing or talking
down to somebody he wants to show that
he's he's this is an indication of
Jetson ca's moral Purity moral what you
call Holiness really
interent
the second reason why Jessa doesn't
mention omnis jonan by name is that he
wants to to acknowledge that the spread
of Buddhism in Tibet is due uh entirely
to the kindness of these great llamas
who came before and uh jet the omnicient
Jona is is an example of one of those
great llamas who came before Jetson Kaba
and help spread Buddhism throughout
Tibet if you look at a person's
spiritual life you can divide divide it
into their worldview and into their
activities and from the point of view of
their activities meaning uh their
bodhicitta uh their feelings of
renunciation their compassion for others
uh that omnicient Jona and other llamas
of of who have come before jet Kapa had
perfect love perfect compassion they
were incredible bonis saas and so Joka
doesn't want to any way imply uh that
they didn't make some incredible
extraordinary beautiful contribution to
the spread of Buddhism in Tibet he
doesn't want to uh say anything to them
he doesn't want to name them directly
because he doesn't want anyone to think
that he doesn't appreciate appreciate or
or that he doesn't understand how much
their love and compassion and teachings
on bicha have caused the spread of
Buddhism in Tibet but on the other hand
from the point of view of their
worldview how they understood emptiness
how they understood uh those subjects he
says Jena's mission was to clarify
things that they actually didn't quite
grasp correctly so he he's not
attacking omnicient Jona directly by
name for that reason but but is trying
very uh very with great effort to
clarify uh the view the world view
especially the understanding of
emptiness uh of these llamas who came
before that that it wasn't very clear or
it wasn't expressed very clearly uh
about emptiness and that's his mission
so that's another second reason why he
doesn't mention the omn J by
name uh that was a a little digression
and now we're jumping forward
again uh so don't think I'm now I'm
going to jump to the other subject so
don't think that's what I just said is
part of the new subject
okay
we're at the fourth line for the bottom
of page nine uh J kab is going to
explain what the Buddha meant when he
spoke about the first group of things
that didn't have any nature of its own
if you remember the Tibetan word can
mean either definition or characteristic
so when the Buddha said uh nothing has
any nature of having any of having any
characteristics of its own uh what did
Lord Buddha mean he's referring of
course to the first attribute or
category uh described by the mind only
School
mhm so the Buddha himself in the Sutra
where he explains what he meant when he
taught the sutras uh says now he goes on
after saying that things don't have any
nature have any characteristic of their
own he goes on to say and what did I
mean when I say that things didn't have
any nature of having characteristics of
their own when I talk about
characteristics or def by definition the
word that I'm referring to is kak
meaning uh we've been translating as
nominal stuff things which are just
nominal remember it refers to unchanging
things after you take out emptiness
okay so now that we know what it was he
was talking about when he said that
things didn't have any characteristics
any nature of having any characteristics
and now that we know that he was talking
about the fact that things which are
nominal uh don't have any nature of
their own uh now that we've established
the thing it is that doesn't have any
nature of its own when you talk about
characteristics not have any nature of
their own now we can go on to explain
how it is that they don't have any
nature of their own and we're going to
do so in two uh in two modes there'll be
the negative mode where we're trying to
refute something about it we're trying
to prove something that it doesn't have
or something that's not true about it
and then we'll go into a positive mode
where we try to establish something
about it in a positive way so here goes
the Sutra explaining why things don't
have any nature of having any
characteristics of their own which
refers to nominal stuff first we'll talk
about what he means in a negative way
and then we'll talk about what he means
in a positive
way yes
sir yes sir
uh this is a now out of the negative one
and the positive one he actually treats
the positive one first so he says what
is the nature of of things that are
nominal uh meaning in in the mind only
School referring to things which are
unchanging but are not not right uh it
refers to the things which are only uh
established through imagination only
established through mental pictures okay
so things which are established that way
we can say they don't they when we say
things that are nominal uh things that
have uh characteristic or don't have
some characteristic we're talking about
things that are imaginary or things that
mainly depend on us picturing
them
uh and now comes the negative side where
uh Lord Buddha says okay from a positive
standpoint these things exist through
conceptualization let's say uh and but
these things don't exist through any
nature of their own or through any by by
definition so he's going on to say that
so we finish the the positive way to say
it is uh these things exist through some
kind of conceptualization the negative
way to say it is that these things don't
have any nature of their own or any by
they don't exist by definition so here
Lord Buddha has for the first time used
the actual wording uh don't exist by
definition before it just said their
charact by their own characteristic or
something so here he's used the actual
word uh they don't exist by
definition
uh so if we express this we go back to
you know Elementary
logic and so it's good for you guys
because you study it this year so it
says we'll go back we'll make a
classical logical statement and I'll
express it that way so we say what's the
church in is a g Church meaning nominal
stuff let's take the things that are
called
nominal they are what the Buddha
referred to in the brief section as
things that don't have any nature of
their own with regard to their
characteristics because and now we get
the T the correct reason and then the
correct reason is going to be divided
into a positive half and negative half
because they are only uh creations of
our Concepts a in a positive way and
then B and because they don't have any
nature of Their Own by definition and
that would be the the negative
expression of that so that would be in a
logical statement you'd say consider all
nominal stuff it doesn't have what the
Buddhist said any nature of having
characteristic of their any nature of
having characteristics why because a
they are products of our Concepts and B
uh they are not such that they exist by
definition
okay
and then from uh the second line of page
10 jetona is undertaking to give an
explanation of the Buddha's own detailed
explanation of what he meant so now now
we're getting jeton capa's take on the
on the Buddha's explanation of what he
meant in that very brief
phrase
uh so now uh this is J Kapa uh
explanation which is kind of a more
detailed explanation of what the Buddha
meant when he gave that positive
explanation and then that negative
explanation so Jess Kaa says why why is
it that the Buddha uh says that uh
nothing has any nature of having
characteristics of its own he says in in
reply to that question Lord Buddha is
saying uh what I meant when I said that
was uh from a negative point of view uh
nothing has nothing exists by definition
nothing exists to its own
characteristics and from a positive
point of view all things are just
creations of your labels and your
Concepts and that's that's what the
Buddhist saying
here uh CA says uh the first two lines
are teaching that now we got to go back
and find those first two lines
okay
sir when JSA on page 10 line two at the
end says the first two lines dot dot dot
he's referring to page n uh fourth line
from the bottom at the end I'm sorry
third line from the bottom where it says
uh the Buddha himself says what do I
mean when I say that nothing has any
nature of having any characteristics of
its own I'll tell you what I mean I mean
that those things which are only exist
nominally don't have any characteristics
of their own or don't exist by
definition so those are the two lines
that J is talking about when he says by
the way the meaning of the first two
lines can be explained in a positive way
negative way and he goes into that
explanation okay
uh these are a question posed to the you
know it's a rhetorical question by the
Buddha and and an answer by the Buddha
in which he indicates that that category
accepted by the minority school called
things that exist nominally uh is
explained as having no Nature by
definition or not having nature of its
own
uh so Justa is is reporting a second
rhetorical question by the Buddha on
page 10 line 4
where he says now why would that be true
okay so you got to jump back to page
nine uh where you have the second line
from the bottom where the Buddha himself
is saying now why would that be the case
and then the Buddha himself goes on to
explain why that would be the case in a
positive way and in a negative way so
jetona recording reporting the second
rhetorical question uh begins on page 10
line4 to say well here's what the Buddha
here's the second rhetorical question
where the Buddha says now why would I
say that and then the Buddha goes on to
explain in a positive way and a negative
way why he would say that what nominal
things don't have any nature of their
own okay uh and and are creations of our
Concepts so in a positive way and a
negative way so he says now the second
rhetorical question uh J cop is going to
clarify for
us sir uh now what they mean when they
say things are a creation of your
Concepts or labels or something like
that and what they mean when they say
things don't exist by definition uh
we're going to get into that in a lot
more detail uh in the next few
days
for
uh the next line which is uh page 10
line uh six at the end uh says um this
opening of your eyes towards the true
meaning of the Sutra and what that means
is Jetson Copa clarification of what the
Sutra means in the two rhetorical
questions in the Sutra uh I'm going to
uh in the latter two in the two which
are to come you can also apply this
explanation of that statement in the
Sutra
uh to the latter two which are to come
what are the latter two which are to
come the other two attributes of the
Mind only school so they're going to
apply uh these two rhetorical questions
to the explanation of what it means to
be dependent and what it means to be uh
I think we're going to get uh Yong which
means The Emptiness of things right so J
says I opened your eyes right here to
the meaning of this two rhetorical
questions now you take that
understanding and don't forget to take
it with you when we go down to the other
two attributes of the Min only school
and it'll help you a lot when you get
down there
okay
uh now the next uh section is very cool
uh jeta is going to go into the point
where you know the mind only School says
that things don't exist by definition
and the Mika the higher schools also say
especially say that things don't exist
by definition what do they mean when
they say that things don't exist by
definition uh the wording is the same
when a a mind only person will say
things don't exist by definition a
middleway person will say things don't
exist by definition but what they mean
is totally different you know what those
words mean to the mind only people and
what those words mean to the middle wave
people is completely different so Jessa
in the section immediately to follow is
going to clarify the distinction uh
between what those two the members of
those two schools mean when they both
say the same thing that things don't
exist by
definition
for
uh so you have this difficult expression
in the Sut where it says things don't
things don't have their own
characteristics things don't have a
nature of having characteristics and now
we've explained it as meaning things
don't have a nature of having of
existing by definition or through their
own characteristics so what do they mean
when they say that in the mind only
school they're saying that when whether
something exists through its own
characteristics or by definition or not
refers to the question of whether or not
they are simply constructs of our
Concepts or not are they simply
constructs of our mind or are they not
simply constructs of their mind if they
are simply constructs of our mind they
don't exist by definition they don't
exist to their own characteristics to
their own nature and if they are not
simply concepts of a mind then they do
have some existence through through
their own nature or by definition so
that's what a mind only person means
that's how they draw the line between
whether or not something exists by
definition or whether or not something
exists through its own characteristics
uh that's what they mean is it or is it
not simply a construct of our mind if it
is simply a construct of our mind then
it doesn't exist by definition or
through its own characteristics if it is
not a construct of our mind then it does
Exist by definition or through its own
characteristics
uh the expression in tobet for existing
naly or this just exists as a concept or
something like that is actually two
different elements it says M Shaka means
uh established by use of labels and
terms okay so you have to remember those
two words you know in the mind only
school when they say it's nominal
they're talking about that it's
established through the use of labels
and terms and those each have their own
special meaning when you say it exists
through labels the word label refers to
its actual name so in the case of a
water picture or something it would be
the word or the sound uh the name water
pcture picture okay but then uh when in
your mind you think this is a picture or
you picture it as a picture and you
think of it as a picture and you have a
mental image of it as a picture that
process is called term here so when you
say uh nominal means exist through names
and terms name refers to its its
physical name the name that people use
for it and then term refers to the the
conceptualization of it as as a vase or
thinking of it as a vase or mental
picture of it as a vase
okay
for
uh so remember that we're in the mind
only school and they're talking about
the meaning of when you say that things
don't exist by definition means that
they are simply constructs of your mind
labels and terms right and but when you
say that don't forget that just because
you've labeled and turn something
doesn't mean that it necessarily exists
okay there are lots of things that you
can imagine that don't exist so there
things that you can imagine that do
exist and there are things that you can
imagine that don't exist and we have to
draw a distinction between that for
example we could take he says uh a
rabbit's horns and he says well maybe
that's not such a good example because
you know uh gishi lar came over and
showed me a postcard from America one
day of a jack rabbit with these horns on
it and uh so I'm not sure if they exist
in America or not maybe they do maybe
that's not such a good example to take
you know uh we better stick to something
more clearly non-existent like uh how
about a flower that grows in midair
without any dirt no water no nothing you
know just grows like here and he says no
that's not really a very concrete
example let's see let's look around find
something this how about these glasses
you know the fact that I'm holding in my
hand glasses which are made of gold okay
the the glasses the eye glasses in my
hand are made of gold okay so when I say
that I'm applying a label to that I'm
saying glasses made of gold there's a
name right there's a word uh there's a
name there now how about a term the term
comes shortly after that you know I say
glasses made of gold and in your mind
pops up this thing of you know glasses
that are shining with yellow metal and
things like that and then already you've
got a term so you've got a a car a label
and a term uh and you've got a a word
and a thought and a and a concept about
it but it that doesn't mean that the
thing that there do exist eyeglasses
made of gold in my room okay so you can
imagine something you can label
something you can construct something
mentally that remember that that doesn't
necessarily mean that it exists
okay
uh you might think to yourself only a
crazy man would start talking about
Golden glasses but you know I just
trying to give you an example
okay AB it didn't
exist uh so Jess kab is trying to point
out here
exist
uh no so don't forget when we talk about
nominal stuff that whether you're a
middle way person or whether you're a
mind only person you're still going to
accept that it doesn't exist by
definition still you're going to say
this is only a constructive I shouldn't
go that way uh still you're going to say
that it doesn't exist by definition but
don't forget that that they mean totally
different things when they talk about
something nonexisting by definition uh
when they say that things are constructs
of names and terms labels and terms
meaning uh words and thoughts when they
say that things are constructs what the
mind only School means when they say
things are constructs of of words and
thoughts and what the middleway people
say when they say things are constructs
of words and thoughts those two things
are totally different what they mean
when they say that when they give it
that positive ex expression things are
just constructs of your mind and
thoughts they have a totally different
meaning in mind when they when they use
those words therefore when they're
talking about the lack of that or when
they're talking about that things don't
exist by definition they have again a
totally different meaning so there's a
totally different and contradictory uh
uh clashing idea of what it means when
we say things don't exist by definition
because there's a totally different idea
of what we mean when we say things are
constructs and what it means to be a
thing by virtue of a construct
okay
for
this is getting a little tough okay uh
where both schools are talking about the
same objects remember they're talking
about what we call nominal stuff okay
they're both talking about they're both
referring to what the mind only School
describes as nominal stuff and and the
point that Jus C wants to make next is
that when you look upon nominal stuff as
a mind only school and try to think of
it as existing by definition then you
are automatically thinking of it as
existing by definition in the way that
the
majima schools explains existing by
definition so I'll say it again when
you're in the mind only school and
you're looking at this nominal stuff and
you're saying I wonder what it would be
to look at it as if it existed by
definition you are automatically then
also looking at it uh as existing by
definition in the way that that
expression is used by the middle way
school but
okay uh if you get into a you know a
formal debate about this in the debate
ground you get into a big hassle
okay uh so I have a question to ask you
okay now don't forget we're sticking to
the mind only school okay okay and when
you're in the mind only school and take
anything that's a nominal let's take
nominal stuff itself for example okay
nominal stuff and you're focusing on
nominal stuff and you're thinking of it
as existing by definition okay you're
trying to think of it as if it were
existing by definition is that a good
state of mind or a bad State of
Mind is that a good perception or a bad
perception to see nominal stuff as
existing by definition in the mind only
School uh the uh
so we agreed you think it's a bad NE you
know it's a wrong state of
mind I just want to check are you all a
single mindstream or do you have
separate mind streams uh because if you
have separate mind streams I would
expect everyone to you know give a
slightly different answer or or everyone
to give an answer but if it's just one
person giving an answer I guess I have
to assume that it's everybody here has a
single mind
stream let's hear an answer
guys School ifue in both schools that
they agree that um nominal stuff would
the same how could it be good or how
could it be negative or positive
the I don't get you he said
the
uh you're right when you say that uh in
in both schools it's wrong to think of
nominal stuff as existing by definition
and now you've jumped to my second
question race you you're really good
because you covered two of my questions
at once before I got to the second
one I asked you whether I had teeth or
not and you answered me yeah you have
teeth
here
uh he's making jokes and making fun of
you and he doesn't want you take any
offense you know like uh uh it's like uh
you're you're you're you're giving him
two answers which is good and uh it's
like you know when I think about
Tibetans they like the Dharma so much
that if they get a chance to go to two
classes you know right one after the
other back to back that they'll
definitely agree they'll say oh yeah
I'll go to both you know and then you
say uh would you like to have a a meal
right after you've already had a meal
you know would you like to come to both
they say they get embarrassed you know
they say well you know I really
shouldn't eat twice uh right one after
the other but and you Americans look
like you're the same you know you have
great faith in the Dharma and you look
like you could take back toback classes
and you'd still come back for more and
so I'm glad to see that you're coming
back for more on the question too
looks like based on that I have to say
you must have a lot of faith in the
Dharma because you like back Tob
backs I I could guess how you were going
to answer even before I asked the
question you guys in general that you
know you seem to be very interested and
and when I ask a question I'd like to
get more answers is
good
for
foree
uh now here's the basis of the whole
hassle between the middleway and the
mind only school on this question what
does it mean for a thing to Exist by
definition what do we mean when we say
that a thing exists by definition uh in
the mind in the if we go to the pranga
the consequence School of the higher
School of the middle way right the
higher School of the middle way says
that when we examine something to to
determine whether or not exists by
definition uh we try to find take any
object let's take a person for example
okay uh there's two kinds of ways of
looking at a person you can just leave
it and not think about his parts or or
trying to find the real person there or
something like that just leave it leave
it alone don't think about where is this
person really there's somebody standing
there somebody's walking somebody's
eating lunch somebody's doing all these
things if you just leave it like that uh
there's a person there and you can't
deny it there's a person there they're
doing something okay uh but if you if
you really look into it and you try to
examine where is the person is the
person in their finger is the person
their finger is the person their hand is
the person their body is their person
any one parts so the parts all together
something like that if you really tear
it apart and go looking for the person
in any of the parts for example of the
person and you keep checking checking
checking to find where is the thing that
I give the name person you know where is
the object that I give the name and the
idea of person if you go into the parts
if you analyze if you rip it apart
you'll get kind of lost in it you won't
find any person so you know you get this
sort of feeling of loss or something
you're looking for a person and you
really can't find any clear person when
you go digging into the person and and
that fact that when you go digging into
and looking for the person in the parts
of the person and wandering around
checking for the person the fact that
you don't find any person is an
indication that person doesn't exist by
definition if you could then find a
person you know digging around in the
parts examining not just satisfied to
say oh he's getting up he's walking he's
eating he's doing this but if you really
go in and try to find the person in all
the parts of the person if you were then
to find a person that would be a person
that existed by definition and that's
what the uh middleway School means when
they say a person exists by Def uh
doesn't exist by definition because if
you if you found something then that
would be a person that did Exist by
definition now the mind only school has
a totally different idea they say if you
wander around looking for the person you
better find something that's the person
you better find something that we call
the person you when you go digging into
the person is the person in their hand
is the person in their parts where is
the person you better find something
because if you don't then there's no
person and when you find something that
person uh that's that's what it means
to that's not what they mean when they
they say you better find that it exists
by definition okay uh when you're
looking for a person okay but remember
before we're talking about nominal
things now we're talking about people
which are not nominal things but when
you go looking for a person uh as a
person you better find something and
when you find it that's existing by
definition so they they have a totally
different idea so the middle way School
says if you don't when you don't find
anything then you've established that it
doesn't exist by definition the my only
School says you better find something uh
when you go looking and that does Exist
by definition okay it's a totally
different uh idea of what it
means huh they're coming at the same
ending there the same result right uh in
name only the same expression but not
they mine only believes that when you
look for a person in their parts you
better find something and you will find
something and in that sense they do
exist the the MAA says when you go
looking for the person the parts you
won't find anything and that's what it
means to not exist by
definition uh you better right now stop
and get that clear in your mind very
carefully because you can't forget it
and you're going to need it later the
mind only school when they say something
doesn't exist by definition what they
mean is when you go looking for the
thing which is given the name person and
you go looking for that thing which is
given the name Person among uh all the
parts of the person you're not going to
find uh the person and that's what it
means not to Exist by definition so you
have to get that clear in your mind when
they say something doesn't exist by
definition what they mean is when you go
looking for the thing which we call
person among the parts of the person and
elsewhere and you don't find and you
don't find anything that means it
doesn't exist by definition if you did
find something which is impossible that
would Exist by definition don't forget
that's what the you got to fix that in
your mind at this point in the class
that that's what the middleway school
thinks when they say something does or
doesn't exist by
definition
uh now we go to the mind only school's
meaning or idea what you mean when you
say something exists by definition or
something doesn't exist by definition
which is totally
different M uh now now when something
exists by definition right in the mind
only school which they say things do
some things do it means that it is not
just the product of our conceptions it
is not just the product of our
conceptualizations but rather from the
object's own side it has some real
existence it has some definitive
existence from its own side without my
thinking about it in a certain way and
to them that means the thing exists by
definition and that means in their in
their thinking this makes something
almost real this means that it has some
reality it's it's got some reality from
its own side it's not totally dependent
on my thinking of it a certain way and
that's what it means to Exist by
definition they don't say that nothing
exists by definition they say that many
things do exist by definition and
existing by definition means it's not
just a product of my Concepts it's not
just a product of my mind it has some
true existence from its own
side
so what does it mean when we say this
object has its own unique way of
existing it it is it is existing from
its own side in its own unique way and
that's a description of any particular
object oh what it's not just I made it
up with my mind it has some unique uh
some some particular existence of its
being that particular object right it
has its own unique way of being that
it's coming from its own side what do
they mean when they say it has some
unique way of being from its own side it
has from its own side some way of being
it's not just a product of my concept
what does the mind only school mean when
they say it has some unique way of being
from its own side it has some true
reality from its own side first of all
what they mean is it has its own causes
it has been produced from its own causes
that's one way of describing what the
mind only School means when they say
objects have some true existence from
their own side of their own okay what
the first thing they mean is that for
example if it has come from its own
causes clearly come produced by other
causes then that thing has some unique
way of being of its
own
Young
nothing and then there's a second way of
describing what it means when the mind
only School says that this object has
some unique existence from its own side
and that is it has some isness it has
some own characteristic nness it has
some own true reality of its own it has
some some kind of true nature of own it
has some kind of unique identity of its
own and and so that's the second meaning
they have when they say uh it exists
from its own side or it has some unique
being from its own way so remember
there's two different kinds of unique
way of being from its own side first one
meaning in the mind only school right
that it that it is coming or it has been
produced by its particular causes that
is a unique way of being second unique
way of being is that it has some sign of
its own Identity or of its own real
nature of its own reality its own own uh
unique uh quality of its own and and
those are the two ways in which the
minority School think that something
must have its own unique way of being
from its own
side I got a question for you guys uh
we're in the mind only School uh mind
only School uh takes all existing
phenomena and groups it into certain
groups how many groups
there H it's a Pity that only one person
can answer it makes me think again that
you all have only one mindstream in in
tibetan class everyone answers like as
one you they all go
three you don't have to yell because you
probably get a sore throat but anyway
try to answer at once uh if not all at
once then you know slowly each person
answer all you know pretty close to each
other uh I guess everyone agrees that
it's
three now careful uh question and I want
a good answer from you all okay uh you
go into those three groups
take your mind into those go through
those three groups mentally uh try to
pick out the groups group or groups that
would involve things which come from
their own causes tell me how many groups
involve things that are coming from
their own causes remember we talked
about its unique nature meaning uh
coming from its own causes how many
groups are there that involve stuff that
comes from its own
causes and what is the name of that
group
you can answer in English and you don't
have to answer
in so you got one anymore
oh okay so you've covered my first half
of my description of something having a
unique nature was coming from its own
sign right which was did it come from
its causes so I I admit you covered that
pretty well now take your mind back to
those three groups and tell me if
there's any objects which seem to have
an ident unique identity of their own or
a unique identity coming from their own
side are there any things in those three
groups that that involve things which
have a unique special identity coming
from their own
side how many how many how many first
decide whether or not any there any in
those groups and then how many of the
things you know how many groups involve
things that have a unique nature that's
coming from their own side
come
uh now I want to change my description
of what it means to have its own nature
or its own identity of its own way of
being let's say if I what happens if I
restrict it to some kind of Ultimate Way
of being some kind of tip toop way of
being some kind of highest way of being
how many of the things in those three
categories have some kind of Ultimate
Way of being some kind of ultimate
identity that
that oh CH
sorry uh so I think uh there must have
been somebody that came with you who
believes the same thing that if you
asked them do you want to come to dinner
they'd say no I don't feel like it right
now but you say you want to come to
Dharma class that they would run to the
Dharma class
so uh you seem to be maybe we got
another Tibetan here not just an
American that's what he's saying okay
the kind of person that would run to a
Dharma class and say I don't have time
for
dinner okay you look you sound like my
piso okay from the same
place okay
which
one uh you showed me the tip of the
iceberg I can guess the rest there you
have to go into a big explanation I know
which one you're talking
about
uh among the three now take your mind
through those three categories again go
through them and tell me which of them
Exist by definition in which of those
three categories are stuff or things
that exist by
definition
two of them
yeah uh so uh here is here we got to the
main belief of the Min only School Alto
together okay which is that two of the
two of the categories or two of the
groups can be said to Exist by
definition and one of them doesn't exist
by definition obviously the one that
doesn't exist by definition according
our school is the nominal stuff because
that's just a construct of your mind but
the emptiness category and then the
other category which is things which
depend on other things which means
caused things right things that come
from causes those two according to their
school do have some definitive nature of
their own they have some definitive
nature of their own and then one of the
categories the nominal stuff category is
really a construct and doesn't have any
definitive nature of its own
and that's the guts of the Mind only
school so don't forget now stick it in
your mind okay
remember oh he says no you better cored
to here stick it in your mind okay
remember what it is when you're in the
mind only school and you think you say
things do have a definitive nature they
do exist by definition remember what it
means it means they are not simply
constructs of my mind they have some
unique way of existing that comes from
their own side and never forget okay
keep that in your mind you have to
remember that for this whole class that
when you're in the mind only school and
when you're a mind only School person
and when a mind only School person says
this thing has some kind of definitive
existence or existence by definition
what they mean is that it's not just a
construct of a mind it has some ultimate
or some unique way of existing that's
coming from its own
side uh so when I say that the M only
School says that uh when when they when
they think of something existing from
its own unique way of being you know
that something exists from its own side
with some with its own unique way of
being how many unique ways of being pop
up in your mind you know how many unique
ways of being from its own side can you
think
of huh not all just all of them as a as
a as a group when when a my only School
person says this thing has some unique
way of being from its own side how many
different unique ways of being are they
thinking of when they say that he went
through that
uh you answered so well that we're going
to stick some extra robes on you and
send you over to debate ground and see
if we can pass you as a
monke
so you agree there's
two yeah unique way of being has two
kinds of flavors of unique way of being
right one is coming from its own cause
and what was the other one the other one
identity
how well how many you guys think there
are B quiet ones in the back
there are your two the same as her
two
you must at this point in this class uh
make sure that you understand now that
the distinction between those two
schools when they from their mouth say
the same words right existing by
definition having some definitive
existence you better know at this point
that they mean totally different things
one school meaning you know something
impossible right the middle way School
saying that's an impossible thing
nothing can exist by definition because
when you go looking for the thing that's
given the name name person you never
will find a thing that's given the name
Person among its parts and if you did
find something which is impossible that
would Exist by definition and in the
mind only school oh that those things
must exist by definition because they
whether or not you think of them in a
certain way whether or not you project
something a certain way they have some
unique way of being from their own side
you better get that distinction straight
now or you're going to blow up your mind
later
uh and don't mix up things you know when
I talked about things having their own
unique identity from their own side
don't forget that this is a unique
belief of the Mind only school don't go
mixing it up with other schools it's
only the mind only school that's talking
about oh this thing having some unique
uh existence or identity of its own
coming from its own side don't forget
that that description of what it means
to Exist by definition or definitive
existence is unique to the Min only
school don't go mixing it up with other
schools
later uh this description of what it
means when the mind only School says
that something has a unique existence
from its own side right those two
flavors of that description is not
something you're going to find written
down in books or you're not going to
find descriptions of That in scripture
this is an oral uh tradition that's been
passed down from person to person and
that's how you're getting it okay so
don't go looking for it in a book this
is a very beautiful uh unique oral
instruction that's been passed down from
from ear to ear he
said
so don't forget that uh conversely when
the M when the middle wave School talks
about something existing by definition
uh and don't remember what they mean
when they say existing by definition
which is impossible according to them
right obviously the mind only school
people will say your description of what
it means to exist definitively or by
definition can't be correct because it
would apply to nothing um but our but
our description of what it means if we
take your description of what it means
to Exist by definition we think that
applies to all things we exist we
believe that when you go looking for the
thing which is given a certain name you
must find it we believe that your
description of what it means not to
Exist by definition actually is not
something which doesn't exist it's
something which does exist and not only
that that every object must have that
okay so we don't agree to the m only
School says to the middleway school your
description of what what it is to Exist
by definition which you say is
impossible with regard to anything we
say it's not only possible but requisite
for every object that exists it surely
when you go to look for the thing that
was given the name you better find
something so we don't accept conversely
the minority School says the middleway
school your description of what it means
to Exist by definition is not only
something that doesn't exist something
must exist must exist with regard to all
existing
things
uh so uh when the when the uh Middle Way
School says that the description of
something existing by definition is
something that if you looked for the
thing which got the name right
ultimately you wouldn't find it the mind
only School flips it around completely
they say every existing object in the
universe
once it exists it must exist in such a
way that when you look for the name
thing that's given the name you must
find it so this is the big uh difference
between the two schools the minority
school is saying that every existing
thing exists in such a way that when you
go looking for the thing that got the
name of the thing you better find it and
the in the majima school is saying when
you go to look for the thing that's
given the name independent the name
right you'll never find it uh that's a
big distinction between these two
schools what
oh tough one here okay uh okay think
about what the the Mima and he
especially when he speaks about MIM he's
talking about pranga the consequence
school so when the consequence School
describes something as existing by
definition right let's talk about it uh
in the in the sense of the Mind only
school's description of nominal stuff
right out of the three groups we're
talking about nominal stuff how does
nominal stuff relate to the the majima
people's description of what it means to
Exist by definition question for you
guys expect an answer
okay you're focusing on nominal stuff is
described by the mind only School how
does that relate to how the mind mik G
School describes things that exist by
definition it would be like um
every
uh
for
uh let's make it a simple yes and no
question okay think of nominal stuff as
described by the mind only school and
tell me whether what the pranga
describes as existing by definition
would apply to it or not okay think of
what the ma means when they say existing
by definition and tell me whether the
category in the mind only school called
Nal stuff has that or
not no
when you say that um p gig's idea what
it is to Exist by definition could never
apply to any of the three groups
excepted by the mind only because it
wouldn't it doesn't even exist are you
putting a majima hat on or are you
putting a m only hat on who's whose
Viewpoint are you staying
from was I asking you the question from
the point of view of a Min only person
or was I asking you the question from
the point of view of a middleweight
person are you inside
uh maybe it's that I didn't translate
very clearly so you didn't know which
school you were supposed to be in anyway
uh I'll say it again more clearly
okay from the point of view of a person
sitting in a from the point of view of a
member of the Mind only school does the
description of what it means to Exist by
definition according to theh G School
applied to the group that the Min only
School says
exist my question was
that that was my
question
oh now we're back to the original point
it's kind of cool so assuming you're a
member of the Mind only School uh and
when you say that the description of the
majima school of what it is to Exist by
definition does apply to our group that
we call nominal stuff and assuming
you're in the minity school don't forget
when you think of nominal stuff as
existing by definition in the way
described by the Monica school is that a
is that a correct state of mind or an
incorrect state of mind don't forget two
of Mind only School
person
uh whoa
sure if you think of if you think of a
nominal object that's
existing uh in a in in a definitive way
as definitive way is described by the ma
Mika are you according to minority
School thinking of that nominal thing in
a wrong way or a right
way so please keep that in your mind
okay got we got to that place don't
forget it according the mind only school
if you think of labeled things in the
way that the maika describes as as
existing by definition you're right on
right you you're thinking of it in just
the right way okay according to to there
manik you're crazy right but according
minority school you're thinking of it
just the right way oh yeah if I look for
the thing that was labeled Winston I
would find the thing that was labed
Winston if I think things that are
labeled right if I think of them that
way oh you're right on okay according to
mind only school you're right on that
kind of thought is perfect
okay okay that brings us back to the
text where we started from like a long
time
ago so we got back to the original text
right when we talking about when a mind
only person regards an object which is
which is nominal right nominal stuff and
they think of it in a way which is uh uh
exists by definition as existing by
definition is described by the majima
school then are they correct yes they
are
okay uh we're on page 10 third line from
the
bottom
so you got to understand the wording
here in the Tibetan means
but if you have the State of Mind in
which you believe that something is
existing by definition then uh with
regard to things that are nominal
then then you must also be regarding
that nominal thing in the in a way uh in
which the Maj Mika School describes as
something existing by definition you
probably you must be seeing it that way
right if you if you see nomal things as
existing by definition then
automatically you must be seeing them in
a way that uh sees them as existing by
definition as as described by the maik
okay
uh it's a problem with the Tibetan you
have to be able to understand the
Tibetan pretty clearly to get what he's
trying to say here but with regard to
nominally existing things that group in
the mind only school called nominally
existing things when you see it as uh
when a when a Min only School person
sees it as existing by definition they
automatically Perce it as existing by
definition in the way that's described
by the man school what Lang Lang uh is
that a problem for you guys or not what
is that hard to catch or does it does it
feel comfortable any questions about it
question yeah condition
yes that seeing the imputed the nominal
stuff
as is is what the mind only is refuting
right uh it's merely uh merely posited
by the label and the
yeah yeah in their school yeah they have
to say
that uh yeah you're right uh things
don't have the definitive existence uh
nominal things don't have definitive
existence as that is uh defined by their
own school right that's true so do you
think that if you were a s if you were a
minority School person and you thought
that things did have definitive
existence as that definitive existence
is explained by their own skull would
that be a correct state of mind or
wrong
yeah exactly right exactly right that's
so far exactly
right now the big question
is in the mind only School uh those
things that are described as nominal by
the mind only school and when they say
that those don't have definitive
existence as we describe definitive
existence okay that state of mind is
correct mean we middle yeah no you are
you are mind only School mind only
school people say that the things that
the mind only school things things are
what we call nominal that they do not
have a definitive existence as described
by the mind only school that's a correct
state of mind now does that State of
Mind think of those same objects as
having definitive existence as the mind
as the Mima people explain it or doesn't
it people think that me people think
nominal things have self-existence is
that no no that's not the question uh
when a mind only School person thinks of
nominal stuff as not having definitive
existence in the way that mind only
school people describe definitive
existence that state of mind which is
correct according to them does that same
state of mind regard those same objects
and think that it does or does not have
definitive existence as described by the
manum
people you're uh
your
cigarettes the
for
for okay now I'm talking about a
different state of mind okay you are in
the mind only school okay you are
thinking about things that we describe
as nominal in the mind only school but
you you're having a problem you're
believing that things do exist by
definition as described by the mind only
school now that is a state of mind which
is wrong right okay so does that wrong
State of Mind think of those same
objects as existing by definition in the
way that the proen Gea describe existing
by definition no no I don't
think they say that the things have
parts and names and that's why um it's
Define but in the other school they're
talking about mental
objects
uh you're pretty much on the right track
it's good you're going the right way
you're on the right
track
but okay so now you're back in the mind
only school and they're looking at those
objects and they say when you look for
the thing that got the name of the thing
without the name of the thing right you
have to say that I think uh which
according to mind me because impossible
right but in their school if you're
looking for the thing that got the name
of the thing uh independent of the name
of the thing do you find it or not they
say yes you do find it you do find it
now is that a wrong state of mind or a
right State of Mind Correct state of
mind or incorrect state
hey come on we're talking School we're
in the school so according
to yeah yeah yeah yeah is that a correct
state of Min them or a wrong state of
Min them that when you look for the
thing that got the name independent of
the name you do find the
thing yeah but you can erase it too you
know you can find a for how long but you
can erase it
uh
so this is this is going to stand for
all nominal stuff okay my my rosary is
going to stand for all nominal stuff in
the
universe
uh so forget ma okay in the mind only
school when you're focusing on this
rosary and this rosary is standing for
everything in the world which is what we
call n which is don't forget refers to
all unchanging things right except for
emptiness don't forget okay so when
you're focusing on that uh and there's a
state of mind that says when I look for
the thing which is labeled that
independent of the label I do find it in
the mind only school is that a good
state of mind or a bad state right state
of mind or wrong state of
mind don't
know so I'll give you I'll give you an
illustration that will help
you is this this is a rosary
right
so no matter what state of whose mind it
is right whose perception it is if a
state of mind looks at this rosary and
says this is a rosary do we put that in
the category of correct perceptions or
incorrect
perceptions no matter who's looking at
it yeah yeah yeah it depends on who's
looking at
it again
that forget my don't forget I'm just
saying you know you just got through a
big dose of Diamond Cutter over and over
again right that's my forget my from the
from the from the M only uh School uh
would any reasonable State of Mind look
at this and say it's a rosary yes yeah
and would that be in the category of
correct states of mind or incorrect
States of
mindre
and then suppose according to minority
school that another person comes with
another state of mind and looks at the
same thing and says that's no Rosary
would that being a good state of mind or
a wrong state of
mind we call that a bad state of
mind so will that stupid state of mind
that wrong State of Mind look at the
rosary and also say yes this is a
rosary
Shake no won't it won't think that
because it's thinking it's not a rosary
right if the mind that had previously
came and said this is not a rosary
suddenly came and said this is a rosary
he wouldn't be in the bad State of Mind
category anymore he would have shifted
over to the good State of Mind category
was
so forget Ma J remember we're in the M
only school and you're looking at this
rosary which is standing for all
unchanging things except for emptiness
right remember nominal things and it
comes up and says uh this thing exists
by
definition and by definition in their
own meaning of the word right which
which state of mind is that is that good
or bad wrong ex by definition as they
Define exist by
definition
yeah now that same state of
mind that takes this in the wrong way
right it in it says this exists by
definition as they describe existing by
definition okay with that state of mind
understand that when you look for the
thing that is named this object you find
it would it say that or
not
yeah say that M only School
SCH with that wrong state of mind that
says this does Exist by definition which
is wrong right yeah about the kund if
that wrong State of Mind came and looked
at kundak and said yes this does Exist
by definition which is wrong even in
their own school right yeah would that
same state of mind come to the Rosary
come to the kundak and say oh oh oh when
I look for the name thing named kunak I
do find something named
kak C
so if you say that the state of mind
which wrongly held that it existed by
definition as existing by definition is
described in their own school if you say
that that same state of mind perceived
that this when you look for the thing
named kund you do find something called
kund wouldn't it shift over from to over
to the good states of mind because it
was right about that
oh
boy last
last you've got a wrong State of Mind in
the mind only school it's looking at K
it's thinking that nominal stuff and
it's thinking that this stuff does Exist
by definition as we describe what
existing by definition means which even
according to them is a wrong state of
mind but if that same state of mind were
to say to itself if I look for the thing
named nominal stuff I do find something
ultimately then wouldn't it according to
their goo shift over to the correct
state of
mind yeah yeah
yeah so uh now is he bad state of mind
or good state of
mind
everything but wouldn't you have to say
it's sort of a mix
yeah that's really too bad you're gonna
amputate this mine into two parts and
say oh this
part uh sounds like you're saying we got
to split him in two
now he's bring us to the point that um
that that's why we could say because
it's no is that what's trying to Pro oh
I know what you mean by
that I don't
know
uh so question for you guys in the
school of the Mind only School in the
mind only school do they say that when
you look at kak things right when you
look at Nally existing things which for
them don't forget is is things that are
like con Concepts or constructions when
you look at them do they in their own
School say that when you look for the
thing which is given the name of of that
do you find it or do they say that you
don't find
it
huh when you say when you say they don't
find it what are you thinking of are you
sticking in here or
what
so I'm thinking
oh yeah didn't
you I have uh closed and locked the door
in my I told you not to go
there uh in the mind schools mind only
school's own beliefs uh when you look at
something which exists by Concepts uh is
it true that when you look for the thing
that was given that name do you find
something so in the mind only school
does that State of Mind belong in the
good minds or the bad states of
mind so that previous state of mind
which said that it did Exist by
definition as they describe existing by
definition in their own school which is
a wrong State of Mind according to you
if it started thinking like that that it
did find something then we'd have to
move on over to the good States
right
uh you were describing you know if we
say it in in terms of people right that
there's some kind of bad person like
some never studies not interested in
Dharma never doing anything and then
suddenly you decide to promote him to
the good side just with regard with
people that'd be a little weird you know
like they don't change that quickly okay
to make up your mind is they on the good
side or the bad side I half does he
still think the other way does he still
think
uh
people can change like that but kind of
State of Mind change like
that
so you got two different states of Mind
here you got one saying that these
objects Exist by definition according to
the way we describe existing by
definition which is a lousy state of
mind and can that lousy State of Mind
suddenly say to itself oh when you look
for the thing that's given the name
nominal stuff you do find it one state
of mind
can
spe
uh it's it's true with regard to to
nominal things that they don't exist by
definition and that and when you do go
looking for the thing that got the name
you independent of the name you do find
it okay that those two things according
to mind only school both apply to
normally existing things but can the
state of mind that says this does not
exist by definition I'm sorry this does
Exist by definition all simultaneously
say this when you look for the thing
that's given its name you do find it can
that
happen from the beginning this has been
my only question
ch
uh when you say that uh one state of
mind has changed to another when you say
that the Mind changes you're not saying
that one state of mind is the other
state of mind you see I mean that's his
real question he's not saying saying can
the Mind Over time change he's saying
can one can the way in which one State
of Mind views things actually be the way
the other state of mind views it are
those two ways of viewing something
contradictory or
not okay let him go ahead let him
go uh okay if you want to raise an
objection go ahead but generally don't
do that okay no go
ahead this whole house will started from
page 10 third line from the
bottom but the book says right there
that if that state of mind is holding
that nominal things uh Exist by
definition then it's also holding that
they exist by definition in the way that
the in the way that the M only School
says it Middle Way School says it is is
that right that's what the text
says
okay did that got that clear I'll say it
again the state of mind which is holding
that it exists by definition as the mind
only School describes it
is also a state of mind which is holding
that it uh exists by definition as in
the way that the person G holded is now
is that possible or not he just got
through saying it wasn't possible with
one state of mind have those two aspects
at the same time they're both
wrong in the Min only school to hold
that imputed
natur is in the minority school is WR in
the minity school you're saying it's
right
no no from the state point of view of
the minor school can one state of mind
hold those have those two aspects at the
same
time
but the book says that with non existing
things that one state of mind can and
does simultaneously believe that it
exist by definition in the way that the
Min only School describes existing by
definition and at the same time believes
that it exists by definition in the way
that the proa holds existing by
definition oh
yeah
uh don't get don't lose yourself in the
words existing by definition or having a
definitive existence now let's go to the
real meaning of it for the ma m for the
middleway people they think that when
you say this thing exists by definition
what you're saying is when you look for
the thing that got the name independent
of the projection independent of the
name you do find an existing thing can
that same state of mind hold it to be
existing by definition in the way that
the mind only School describes existing
by definition we just got done saying
it but if you accept what the book says
itself at this point and you try to
think about it that way it's a big house
right there's a big problem
here ah now we got a philosophical mess
and we got to clean up this
philosophical
mess
for
Fore
fore
uh you have to do some like gymnastics
to get to the uh to the way in which
this this and he's really he likes this
kind of stuff H you have to get the some
kind of twisting around to get it to be
correct here because he's saying uh one
state of mind is holding that it does
Exist by definition right exist does
Exist by definition and that same state
of mind is viewing it uh as existing by
definition in the way that the Maj Mika
explain existing by definition and in
the mind only school you can't do that
you can't say those two things at the
same time if you were saying it existed
by definition in the mind only school
that's a wrong state of mind uh if you
say it exists by definition as the mind
we can explain it in the mind only
school that's a correct state of mind
because then you'd be saying that when
you look for the thing that got the
project
independent of the protection it really
has existence so if you take this on
face value this statement that in the
mind only school one state of mind could
hold it as existing by definition and at
the same time hold it existing by
definition as the pro G can explain it
that'd be an impossible state of mind so
you can't explain it that way so you
have to look at the first half of that
where it says the mind is holding that
it exists by definition and it you have
to say that that state of mind is not
what it sounds like you have to
concentrate on that state of mind saying
this object is something that
exists by definition you see what I mean
it's concentrating on the existing part
and not on the existing by definition
okay so when you explain this passage
when you get to this passage that state
of mind is not so much fixated on
whether it exists by definition as
explained by the mind only School that
state of mind is fixated on the question
of does this thing exist or not okay and
then the B definition is just sort of an
aside okay so if you say according to
mind only school can there be one state
of mind that says about one object at
the same time this this does exist and
it does Exist by definition in the way
that the Min that the Maj mik explains
it is that okay that's okay that's okay
if you kind of don't say that by
definition in the first half too loud
okay and you're concent on the existence
part and not the B definition part you
know because because here it's a little
bit different the wording is not quite
by definition they left out a syllable
it doesn't
say it
says exists by itself you got caught
okay it doesn't
say it just
says which in philosophy means have its
own existence doesn't mean have its own
definitive existence
the definitive part got left out here
look carefully and there's
noik okay there not there so really the
first state of mind is just saying this
thing exists it has its own way of being
and it exists by definition as in the
way that the mind and the manik explain
it that's okay that's no problem you got
hung up on theik doesn't say ten go look
at it page 10 third line from the bottom
just as wrong Tinky of that was a long
syllable
uh although I have previously locked the
majima door two or three times and not
let you go there now I'm going to unlock
the door we're going to sneak in there
for a bit and I'll give you an example
an illustration from the other side of
that
door
I'll go to the other side of that door
to that other room called majima school
I'll pick up a little illustration since
you guys had somebody mik teaching
before and I'll bring it back out to the
m only School uh room and I'll show it
to you and you'll catch
it
uh for example if we go to the Maj room
right and we pull out the ma a belief
that a water pitcher has no true
existence right the state of mind that's
looking at the water pitcher and says
right independent on my projections
right this water picture has no true
existence that's a wrong state of mind
that's not a correct state of mind but
in in one sense it's a correct state of
mind because it is attributing to a vas
existence it is attributing to the
picture some existence in one corner of
that state of mind is a little sliver of
state of mind that's saying this thing
exists because you're saying it does
truly exist or yeah yeah because it says
it does truly exist when a wrong state
of mind says about a water picture this
thing exists truly there's a sliver of
correctness about it because somewhere
in that state of mind is thinking that
the water piture exists so from that
State of Mind very good example he says
very good example for understanding this
particular line
okay
he's not correct about the mo of his
existence but it's correct about his
existence so it's got a little
correctness in
it uh you better take that illustration
and carry it over here to this sentence
or else you're going to be in trouble
you're going to have to use that
illustration and take park it over here
in this sentence and use what you
learned from that illustration here or
you're going to be in
trouble
that's a just an illustration I'm trying
to give you so you can take it over to
the mind only school and try to
understand it
better
uh for example I I think I got it
straight there's somebody doing their
they're doing a rosary of and they're
doing it kind of
quick and somebody else looks at them
and might say uh they're not doing it
very sincerely or they're not doing very
well right it's a good state of mind or
a wrong state of mind it's actually a
wrong state of mind but somewhere in
that state of mind is the perception
that this person is reciting so from
that point of view he is perceiving that
the person is is reciting om he's
correct he's incorrect In His assumption
about the other person's state of mind
about how they're doing the OM but
there's a sliver of correctness about
his State of Mind even as he thinks this
person is not serious about their own
man uh these are just uh illustrations
that are that are similar to this other
case
uh when we get to philosophical
conundrums in the text we got to
approach them and we got to resolve them
and this is one way of resolving this
particular hassle in this particular
book this book is famous for having
these very very difficult statements in
it and you have to wrestle with them and
come to some kind of conclusion like
this uh you can't go up to a work by the
great glorious jeton Kaa and say oh it
looks like you made a slipped here you
know I made a boo boo here you must
approach it from the point of view of
he's correct he's trying to teach us
something and what is it we're supposed
to realize
here you've been sitting here for two
and a half hours you better stop here
you guys going to die okay so we'll
leave it there and we'll come back later
okay touch you ready Ana then leave
quickly smoothly cleanly that's a custom
okay
Guru